Guide to the George Augustus Lofton Papers, 1784-1941 RL.00818
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George Augustus Lofton papers
1784-1941
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lofton, George Augustus, 1839-1914
RL.00818
14.2 Linear Feet
1800 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The George Augustus Lofton Papers (1874-1941) were purchased by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1989.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1839, Dec. 25 Born, Panola County, Miss.
1861 - 1865 Served in the Confederate States of America, 9th Georgia Battalion Artillery
1865- 1867 Principal, Wade Academy, Webster County, Ga.
1867- 1868 Admitted to bar; practiced at Americus, Ga.
1868- 1869 Ordained Baptist minister; pastor of several country churches in Georgia
1870- 1872 Pastor, Dalton, Ga.
1871 A.M., Mercer University, Ga.
1872-1877 Pastor, First Church, Memphis, Tenn.
1873-1876 President, Southern Baptist Publishing Society
1877-1884 Pastor, Third Church, St. Louis, Mo.
1880 D.D., Baylor University (Tex.)
1885-1887 Pastor, Talladega, Ala.
1888 Pastor, Central Church, Nashville, Tenn.
1889 President, State Board Missions, Tenn. Authored Character Sketches Moderator, Nashville Association of Baptist Churches
1897 Authored Harp of Life
1899 Authored Baptist Reformation, 1611-1641, A.D.
1900 LL.D., University of Nashville
1902 Authored The Master Wheel
1914, Dec.11 Died
Collection Overview
The George Augustus Lofton Papers span the years 1874-1941, although the bulk of the material dates from 1875-1900. They consist of correspondence, writings and sermons, clippings, book reviews, and printed materials. The collection principally relates to Lofton's career as a Baptist minister serving churches in Dalton, Gal; Memphis, Tenn. (First Church); St. Louis, Mo. (Third Church); Talladega, Ala.; and Nashville, Tenn. (Central Church). The collection mostly contains handwritten sermons and sermon notes, and includes little family or personal material, although a few family letters are in the Correspondence Series. The Correspondence Series, however, primarily contains letters critiquing Lofton's works, Review of the Question and Bible Thoughts and Themes. The Writings and Speeches Series documents Lofton's intellectual growth throughout his career as author and minister. This series also contains Lofton's published text, Character Sketches (1890), and a manuscript draft of his autobiography titled, My Family Garden. Lofton's sermons and sermon notes track both his spiritual development and writing skills throughout the years of his ministry. The sermon notes reveal his views on slavery, capital punishment, and foreign mission work. The Printed Materials Series includes published brochures and sermons written by Lofton and others, 1881-1914. The Miscellaneous Series contains an assortment of items from 1873-1940 including Lofton family photographs and other materials. Included are items pertaining to Baptist minister George Law Stewart and Dr. Adiel Sherwood.
Sermons -- Baptist; Baptists -- Clergy; Capital punishment -- Southern States; Slavery -- United States -- Emancipation; Authors, American -- Southern States; Mission -- Sermons; Lofton, George Augustus, 1839-1914; Stewart, George L.; Sherwood, Adiel, 1791-1879
- Correspondence Series, 1877-1921, undated
  - 1877-1921, undated (Box 1)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1870-1900, undated
  Arrangement note
  Three subseries: Manuscripts, Sermons (arranged alphabetically), and Sermon Notes. My Family Garden is a history of the Lofton family.
  - Manuscripts Subseries
    - Character Sketches, 1890 (Box 1)
    - Draft, My Family Garden, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons Subseries
    - A - Accountability (Box 1)
    - Acquaintance - Address (Box 2)
    - Address - All Important (Box 2)
    - The All Important Question (Box 2)
    - All in All - Always (Box 2)
    - American - Angel's (Box 2)
    - Answer - Atheistic (Box 2)
    - Atonement - Awakened (Box 2)
    - B - Baptist (Box 3)
    - Baptist Faith - Barren Fig (Box 3)
    - The Baptist Trophy, 1876 (Box 3)
    - Bearing Each - Besetting Son (Box 3)
    - Best You Can - Bible Doctrine (Box 3)
    - Bible in the Public Schools - Bible Theory of Sanctification (Box 3)
    - Bible Thoughts and Themes for Young Men - Blessedness of Giving (Box 3)
    - Blind Bartnaeus - Boodle and Whiskey (Box 4)
    - Bread of Life - By-path Meadow (Box 4)
    - Capital Punishment: The Law of God and Nature - Causal Things Without Effect (Box 4)
    - Causes of Spiritual Declension - Child likeness: the Condition of Entrance Into God's Kingdom (Box 4)
    - Christ at the Door - Christ the Door (Box 4)
    - Christ, the Only Personal... - Christ's Example of Activity (Box 4)
    - Christian Charity - The Christian's High Vocation (Box 4)
    - The Christian's Prize - Church Independence (Box 5)
    - Church of the Living God - Church Sunday Entertainment (Box 5)
    - The Cities of Refuge - The Coming of Christ (Box 5)
    - The Coming Empire - Communion with Christ (Box 5)
    - The Compassion of Christ - The Condition of Revival (Box 5)
    - Conditions of Spiritual Prosperity - Conscience (Box 5)
    - Consistency - Crime and Misfortune of Ignorance (Box 5)
    - The Crisis of the Cross - The City of Despair (Box 6)
    - Crystallizing Force of Habit - David's Sin (Box 6)
    - David's Sins - Death and Judgment (Box 6)
    - Debit Without Credit - The Devil as an Angel of Light (Box 6)
    - The Devil's Shake - Did Christ Come to Save the Gentiles (Box 6)
    - Dignity and Moral Effect of Work - The Divine Purchase (Box 6)
    - The Divine Evolution - The Divine Pastoral of Ruth (Box 6)
    - The Divine Signet - Doing and Knowing (Box 7)
    - The Doodle bug - The Drunkard Maker (Box 7)
    - Ecclesiastical Obedience to Pastoral Rule - Efficient Service (Box 7)
    - The Efficiency of the Spirit - Elijah and the Ravens (Box 7)
    - Elijah No. 1 - Eloquence: A Virtue (Box 7)
    - The Exhalation of Joseph - The Endowment of the Holy Spirit (Box 7)
    - Ephraim Joined to his Idol - Essentials to Cross Bearing (Box 8)
    - Esther's Faith and Courage - Eternity (Box 8)
    - The Eternity of Hell - Everybody's Doing It (Box 8)
    - Evidence of Genuineness - Excellency of the Knowledge of Christ (Box 8)
    - Existing Errors Regarding Immorality and the Future State - Faith the Only Medium of Grace (Box 8)
    - Faith, the Result of Ordination - Faithful in Little Things (Box 8)
    - The Faithful Saying - The Fall of Satan (Box 8)
    - The Family Alter - A Fast Young Man (Box 9)
    - Fatal Fall and Final Triumph of Man - The Final Triumph (Box 9)
    - Final Fixedness of Habit - The First Great Victory (Box 9)
    - The Fixed Heart - Forgetting the Things Behind (Box 9)
    - Forgiveness - The Fountain and Issues of Life (Box 9)
    - The Friend of Publicans and Sinners - The Fruitfulness of Death (Box 10)
    - Full Assurance - The Fullness of Christ 3 (Box 10)
    - The Fullness of Christ 4 - Future Punishment (Box 10)
    - Future Reward and Punishment Alike Eternal - The Glory of the Cross (Box 10)
    - The Glory of the Cross - Go Forward (Box 10)
    - God a Consuming Fire - God's Good Things (Box 10)
    - God's Goodness a Motive to Repentance - God's Kingdom and Righteousness First (Box 10)
    - God's Ownership and Service - God's Peculiar People (Box 11)
    - God's People - The Golden Calf (Box 11)
    - Our Golden Calves - Gospel Fishing (Box 11)
    - The Gospel Fountain - The Grace of Compromise (Box 11)
    - The Grace of Liberality - The Great Advocate (Box 11)
    - The Great Commandment - Great is Diana of the Epliesiaus (Box 11)
    - The Great Invitation - The Great Salvation (Box 11)
    - The Great Salvation - The Great Supper (Box 12)
    - The Greatest Wrong - Habitual Drinking (Box 12)
    - Habitual Drinking and It's Remedy - The Half Has Never Been Told (Box 12)
    - The Hardship of Sin - Heaven (Box 12)
    - Heavenly Citizenship - Heredity (Box 12)
    - The High Rock - The Honor Christ (Box 12)
    - Hope - How to Build the Church (Box 13)
    - How to Convert Sinners - I Gave My Life for Thee (Box 13)
    - Ignored and Discarded - Immortality (Box 13)
    - Immorality-Natural - Immortality Typical II (Box 13)
    - Immutability of God's Love in Christ - The Impotency of the Sword (Box 13)
    - The Incompatible Witness - Inferences from the Breckenridge Trial (Box 13)
    - Insecurity - Isaiah's Fig Potilla (Box 13)
    - The Jesus of the Age - Is There at Hell... (Box 14)
    - Is There a True Christianity in the World To Day - John the Baptist (Box 14)
    - John's Gospel - Joseph the Dreamer (Box 14)
    - Joshua's Decided Religion - The Judgment (Box 14)
    - Judicial Blindness - Knowing the Unknowable, Measuring the Immeasurable (Box 14)
    - The Knowledge of Christ - The Last Enemy (Box 14)
    - The Last Enemy is Ours (Box 15)
    - The Last Judgment - Lessons From the 1st Miracle (Box 15)
    - Lessons From the Valley of the Dead - Liberty: the Genius of Christianity (Box 15)
    - Liberty, Part 1 - The Light of God's Countenance (Box 15)
    - The Lilly in the Bag - Loathing God's Lightbread (Box 15)
    - Dr. Lofton's 19th Anniversary - The Lord's Supper (Box 16)
    - Loss of Moral Resistance - Lot's Temptation (Box 16)
    - Lot's Wife - The Love of Christ...Part 2 (Box 16)
    - The Love of Christ... - Love's Epitome (Box 16)
    - Love's Labor Not Lost - Man's Fearful and Wonderful Being (Box 16)
    - Man's First Commission - Marriage (Box 16)
    - Me - The Messicaic Symbolism of Great Pyramid (Box 17)
    - Microscopic Observations - The Mighty Minority (Box 17)
    - Mighty to Save - The Miracle of the (?) Demoniacs and Il-Lessions (Box 17)
    - A Miraculous Deliverance - Mission of John the Baptist (Box 17)
    - The Missionary Zeal of Christianity - Modern Paganism (Box 17)
    - Modern Perils - More to Follow (Box 17)
    - The Mother and the Model Child - Municipal Righteousness (Box 18)
    - Murder and Capital Punishment - Nashville Under the Electric Laugh (Box 18)
    - Nashville's Stumbling Blocks - Nelson Merry Memorial (Box 18)
    - The New Creature - Ninth Anniversary Sermon (Box 18)
    - No Other Name - Non-Resistance as a Force (Box 18)
    - Not Ashamed of the Gospel - Now (Box 18)
    - Obedience - One Thing Needful (Box 19)
    - The Only Religion of Life... - The Only Way (Box 19)
    - Opportune Activity - Our Home Mission Resources (Box 19)
    - Our Institutions of Vice - Our Superior Righteousness (Box 19)
    - Our Sympathetic High Priest - Parable of the Talents (Box 19)
    - Passover - Paul at Antioch (Box 19)
    - Paul at Melita - Paul in Rome (Box 19)
    - Paul in Shipwreck - Paul's Encouragement at Corinth (Box 20)
    - Paul's Good Fight - Paul's Metaphors (Box 20)
    - Paul's Metaphors, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Paul's Metaphors - A Peculiar People (Box 20)
    - The Penitent's Prayer - Perfection (Box 20)
    - Perfection - Perseverance of All Saints (Box 21)
    - Personal Effort - Peter's Confession (Box 21)
    - Peter's Deliverance - The Philosophy of Fear (Box 21)
    - The Philosophy of Prayer - Possibilities of Faith (Box 21)
    - Possibilities Without Culture - Power of Religious Education (Box 21)
    - The Power of the Holy Ghost - Prayer (Box 21)
    - The Preacher in Politics - Prejudice (Box 21)
    - Preservation of All Saints - Procrastination (Box 22)
    - Procrastination of Felix - The Province of Faith (Box 22)
    - The Province of the Sword - The Real Presence (Box 22)
    - Reasoning Together - Relation of Christianity to Law and Order (Box 22)
    - Religion and Crime - The Religious Memories of the Confederate Soldier (Box 22)
    - Remarkable Conversations: Cornelius Remarkable Conversations: Saul (Box 22)
    - Remarkable Conversations: Simon Magus - The Rending of the Veil (Box 23)
    - The Rending Veil - Respect for the Sacred (Box 23)
    - Responsibility According to Ability - Resurrection f Lazarus (Box 23)
    - Revitalization - That Richmond Ring (Box 23)
    - The Rights of Property - Running Against Hindrances (Box 23)
    - Ruth - The Safety of Loyalty (Box 23)
    - Salvation and Security - Sanctification (Box 23)
    - Saul a Persecutor - Saved by Water (Box 24)
    - Saving Others, Not Himself - Science Falsely so Called (Box 24)
    - Scriptural Figures Illustrative of the Spirit's Coming and Work - Seeking God While He May be Found (Box 24)
    - Seeking and Saving the Lost - The Self Confident Fool (Box 24)
    - Self Consecration Part 1 - Self Denial (Box 24)
    - Self-Denial - The Seven Beatitudes (Box 24)
    - The Shepard and the Sheep - The Sin of Ignorance (Box 24)
    - The Sin Unto Death - The Sinner's Self-Judgment (Box 25)
    - The Smitten Rock - Solomon, a type of Christ (Box 25)
    - The Somewhat and the Few Things Which Ruin Churches - Southern Baptist Convention (Box 25)
    - Soul Winning as a Vocation - The Spirit of Christ (Box 25)
    - The Spirit Power - The Stone Before the Spulchur (Box 25)
    - The Stone Ezel - Submission (Box 25)
    - Succession - Sunday Schools (Box 26)
    - Sunday Visitation - The Sy (?) Woman (Box 26)
    - Symmetrical Development (Box 26)
    - Taffy - The Test of Fidelity (Box 26)
    - The Test Question - Thanksgiving (Box 26)
    - Thanksgiving (Box 26)
    - Thanksgiving - Things Settled (Box 27)
    - Thinking and Believing - Through Death to Life (Box 27)
    - The Thought That Turns - To Day (Box 27)
    - Tomorrow - Training of Children (Box 27)
    - The Trail of Christ - Trial of Abram's Faith (Box 27)
    - The Trinity of Graces - My Trip to Europe 3 (Box 27)
    - The Triumphant Cross - Trust In God (Box 28)
    - The Truth as in Jesus - the Two Ways (Box 28)
    - The Unanswerable Argument - Universal Dominion of Christ (Box 28)
    - The Universality of Missions - The Unrighteous Mammon (Box 28)
    - Unused Forces Among Southern Baptist - the Value of the Soul (Box 28)
    - The Value of Time - Vanity Fair (Box 28)
    - Verily! Verily! - the Voice of Conscience (Box 28)
    - The Wages of Sin - Walking on the Sea (Box 29)
    - A Wasted Life - The Way, The Truth, The Life (Box 29)
    - The Way to Have More - The Weeping Christ (Box 29)
    - Weeping Mothers of Jerusalem - On What Side Are You? (Box 29)
    - What Shall the Harvest Be - Where Are We? (Box 29)
    - Where Are We? - Where Are We in Society? (Box 29)
    - Where Are We In Discipline - The Whole Bunch Sin Offering (Box 29)
    - Why Do I Do Right - Without Excuse (Box 30)
    - The Witness of Christ - Work (Box 30)
    - The Work of a Decade - Worldliness and Its Remedy (Box 30)
    - The World's Christmas - The Young Man and His Difficulties (Box 30)
    - The Young Man and His Success - The Youth of Saul (Box 30)
    - Sermons, untitled, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Sermons, untitled, 6 folders (Box 31)
  - Sermon Notes Subseries
    - Account of Francis Baupfield - Attraction of the Cross (Box 32)
    - Baptism - Business (Box 32)
    - Calling and Use of Men - The Citizenship of Freedom (Box 32)
    - The Cleansing Blood - Deeper Water (Box 32)
    - The Deity and Supremacy of Christ - Driving nails for God (Box 32)
    - The Easy Yoke and the Light Burden - Falling Into God's Hands Unprepared (Box 33)
    - The Fear of Opportunity - The Glory of the Cross (Box 33)
    - The Golden Calf - House Missions (Box 33)
    - Hope of the Godless - Is Life Worth Living (Box 33)
    - The Issues of Life - Liberty (Box 33)
    - Life Insurance - Millennium (Box 33)
    - Ministerial Relief - Our Bethels (Box 34)
    - Our High Calling - Prayer (Box 34)
    - Predestination - The Reasonable Hope (Box 34)
    - The Reign of God - The Sin Unto Death (Box 34)
    - Sliding from God - The Sunrise of Christianity (Box 34)
    - The Temporal and the Eternal - The Two Mays (Box 35)
    - The Unattained - What Baptists Stand For (Box 35)
    - What is Prayer - The World for Christ (Box 35)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 35)
- Miscellaneous Series
  - Printed Material,1881 - 1914, undated (Box 35)
  - Clippings,1889 - 1920s, undated (Box 36)
  - Legal Papers and Family Photographs
    - General,1873 - 1912, undated (Box 36)
    - Sherwood, Dr. Adiel, undated (Box 36)
    - Stewart, George L., 1918-1940, undated (Box 36)